Sundaram Ananthanarayanan

https://www.sundaram.io

me@sundaram.io +1(650)-666-9264

SUMMARY

An infrastructure engineer with great passion for performance and scalability. Most recently I have been working on a highly scalable, low-latency stateful task execution system that handles Uber's CI workloads. Before that, I researched extensively on techniques to guarantee ACID like properties for large monorepos and built a state-of-the-art change management system utilized by 3000+ services and 10+ apps at Uber.

EDUCATION

Stanford University

Stanford, CA

Master of Science in Electrical Engineering; GPA: 3.9/4.0

Sep. 2012 - Jun. 2014

College of Engineering, Guindy, Anna University

Chennai, India

Bachelor of Engineering in Information Technology; GPA: 9.32/10.0

Aug. 2008 - June. 2012

WORKING EXPERIENCE

Uber

San Francisco, CA

Senior Software Engineer II

May 2016 - Present

- SubmitQueue: 1000s of engineers committing changes concurrently to a repository leads to frequent master breakages. Explored & conceived a new system called *SubmitQueue* that guarantees an always-green master at scale. At Uber, *SubmitQueue* handles 1000s of commits/hr submitted by 1000s of engineers every day.
 - * Led a team of 5 engineers to build the system: reading papers on state-of-the-art techniques used in similar domains such as Databases, experimented with various approaches to find a scalable solution, & architected the system to handle 1000s of changes/hr.
 - * Improved the shippability of an average service from 52% to 100% while keeping the maximum overhead at 20 minutes to commit a change.
 - * Published a research paper presenting the design & implementation of SubmitQueue at Eurosys'19. Adrian Coyler has covered it as part of the morning paper.
- **uCI**: Because existing open-source CI systems such as Jenkins do not scale to Uber's needs, I conceived & designed *uCI* a large-scale distributed system to handle reliable execution of millions of stateful tasks every day on 1000s of CI machines.
 - * Leading a team of 6 engineers to design a state-of-the-art cluster scheduler that handles faults gracefully (reliability), exploits data locality to come up with optimal placements (performance), scales horizontally on every layer (scalability), and finally guarantees isolation at task/resource levels.
 - * Designed the system leveraging existing open-source technologies such as Apache Mesos for cluster management, Cadence for workflow orchestration & Docker for executing tasks in a containerized environment.
 - * Sped up build times for Android CI workflows by 4-6x, reducing hour-long workflows to order of minutes.

Baidu Research Silicon Valley AI Lab

Sunnyvale, CA

Software Engineer

Jan 2016 - May 2016

• **Speech Infrastructure**: Designed & productionized deep-learning based Speech Recognition APIs which power Android apps such as TalkType. Also worked on infrastructure that would suggest words as you speak (e.g, <u>world</u> level suggestion [word, wide]) .

Twitter Inc

San Francisco, CA

Software Engineer Jun 2014 - Jan 2016

• AddressBook Infrastructure: System for storing, retrieving contacts stored on the phone-book of Twitter's 300M+ MAUs. It was used in powering features such as Who To Follow aimed at user increasing engagement. Designed a scalable offline infrastructure that periodically reconciled the 1PB+ HDFS snapshot with updates in minutes by making use of algebraic structures such as Monoids.

Ancient History

Microsoft

Software Engineering Intern, Kernel Core Team

Redmond, WA

Jun 2013 - Sep 2013

Google Summer of Code

Worked on Metalink Support for Google Chrome

Chennai, India Jun 2012 - Sep 2012

University of Waterloo

Research Intern - Worked on design & application of One-Instruction Processors

Waterloo, Canada Apr. 2011 – June. 2011

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Sundaram Ananthanarayanan, Masoud Saeida Ardekani, Denis Haenikel, Balaji Varadarajan, Simon Soriano, Dhaval Patel, and Ali-Reza Adl-Tabatabai. "Keeping Master Green at Scale". In: Proceedings of the Fourteenth EuroSys Conference 2019, Dresden, Germany, March 25-28, 2019. 2019, 29:1–29:15. DOI: 10.1145/3302424.3303970. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3302424.3303970.
- [2] Dario Amodei, **Sundaram Ananthanarayanan**, et al. "Deep Speech 2: End-to-End Speech Recognition in English and Mandarin". In: *Proceedings of the 33nd International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML 2016, New York City, NY, USA, June 19-24, 2016.* 2016, pp. 173–182. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v48/amodei16.html.
- [3] Sundaram Ananthanarayanan, Siddharth Garg, and Hiren D. Patel. "Low cost permanent fault detection using ultra-reduced instruction set co-processors". In: *Design, Automation and Test in Europe, DATE 13, Grenoble, France, March 18-22, 2013.* 2013, pp. 933–938. DOI: 10.7873/DATE.2013.196. URL: https://doi.org/10.7873/DATE.2013.196.
- [4] Aravindkumar Rajendiran, **Sundaram Ananthanarayanan**, Hiren D. Patel, Mahesh V. Tripunitara, and Siddharth Garg. "Reliable computing with ultra-reduced instruction set co-processors". In: *The 49th Annual Design Automation Conference 2012, DAC '12, San Francisco, CA, USA, June 3-7, 2012.* 2012, pp. 697–702. DOI: 10.1145/2228360.2228485. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/2228360.2228485.

SELECTED TALKS

• Keeping Master Green at Scale

- Slides: https://sundaram.io/slides/submitqueue.pdf
- o Google Journal Club, May 2019

o Eurosys'19, March 2019

o Facebook, Jan 2019

San Francisco, CA

Dresden, Germany

Menlo Park, CA

SKILLS

- Languages: Java, Scala, C++, Bash, SQL
- Specialities: distributed systems, graph theory, algorithms, machine learning, performance tuning and debugging